welcome William Gart to the fourth
active inference Symposium we're looking
forward to your session titled an
introduction to NGC learn a
computational neuroscience libr Library
over to you yeah so today I'm here to
talk about um The Knack the nor adaptive
Computing Labs uh python n Tool uh
called NGC learn uh that is really
focused on getting your ability to
prototype your ideas and work with your
ideas in the field of computational
Neuroscience quickly and efficiently in
Python um so before we're going to start
off with all this first we kind of want
to briefly cover what we mean when we
talk about computational Neuroscience so
this is just the study and investigation
of brain function using mathematical
computation and tools and theories um we
have a focus on uh biologically
plausible and biologically grounded
systems and neur uh neurons and neuronal
systems and we pay very high attention
to the uh constraints Dynamics uh that
are found in the real world when we talk
about these uh for instance we model
things like you know we have the
resistance for membrane potentials we
have currents we have a bunch of other
various uh internal components to
everything that make sure that we are
modeling Faithfully uh all of the
neurons and components that we can find
inside NGC learn um and it we don't just
take from humans uh in fact there's a
couple of various things that we have
that are based on uh findings uh for
things like rat hippo cample neurons and
whatnot for stuff like synaptic
plasticity and
transfers um and so yeah so we kind of
look at this biological interpretation
of the world and so one of the main
things that we also like to look at is
like what is realistic when we talk
about an interpretation of our world and
how biology looks at it and so like for
instance our human eyes it's been
studied that they process think
information at about 60 frames a second
we can certainly detect things that move
through our visual field faster than
that but as far as like visual updates
and whatnot once you pass 60 frames a
second or 60 updates per second we have
a hard time
distinguishing and then also processing
for a lot of things in our brain is not
just we see an image we process the
image once and then we just sit around
idle until a new image comes into our
brain um a lot of the time what we'll
end up with is we'll end up with a
continuous stream of data coming into
our brain and then we have to do
continuous updates and processing on
that and it's that continuous update and
proc processing that we're really are
trying to uh hone in on and identify
here uh we also uh so we do all of this
inside of a biological framing uh so we
use neurons now these are not
necessarily neurons like deep neural
networks like to talk about neurons
where it's just an abstract point in
space uh we actually model them as uh
physical objects uh that have things
like internal States um and that also uh
embody what they look like in brains and
just other neural structures in the body
um we have our uh we have our like the
cell the center of the cell where we
store a lot of our values we have
synapses that connect these to other
neurons later down and one of the key
things that our library very much
highlights is the use of spikes in
spiking neural networks in order to
actually achieve all of this happening
um what this means is that instead of
working in continuous values where you
have a real valued image coming into
your network um and then it passes
through your entire network as a bunch
of other real valued numbers uh images
as they enter into our networks tend to
be converted into what are known as
Spike trains uh which are just a bunch
of discret either ones or zeros on
whether or not there is signal and then
from uh from neurons to neurons in our
systems we tend to transmit these things
only as uh spikes so everything is dealt
with with disc
signals rather than continuous
signals um and then the other thing that
we really heavily rely on in NGC learn
is stateful modeling uh so as we're
dealing with these models that are
constantly taking in signals over time
um it's to be expected that we require
many signals and many iterations over
the signals uh before we will actually
produce any given output what that means
is that all of our neurons have internal
States and are stateful and so we can
for instance stop getting any input and
we can actually still watch what happens
to the neurons models as they basically
return to their rest
positions um and so we have our
biological components that have our
internal States and then these states do
change over time and so we tend to think
about all of the models that we build
with NGC learn and just computational
Neuroscience in general uh somewhat akin
to State machines uh with the idea that
we progress Through Time by changing the
state over own model and then there's
certain actions that happen that can
affect our model and transform it from
one state to
another um and so that's kind of the
basic framing behind what we're going
for with this right we're not trying to
be the next tensorflow we're not trying
to be the next deep neural network
library uh what we're trying to be is
we're trying to be a library that is
specifically catered to computational
neuroscience and the biologically
inspired biic
systems um so why do we need this uh so
build these complex systems has a lot of
overhead if we need to make a system
that tracks all of the different
internal states of all models uh and can
communicate between different components
easily uh that can run efficiently um so
at the bottom here you can see here so
in one of these models that we built
early on uh we had a pretty standard d
uh spiking neural network uh that was
not big by neural network standards uh
that took about about eight hours to do
an Epoch of amnest um just and that is
due to the fact that when we are looking
at an individual image in amnest we have
to go over it uh I think this model was
go it was doing 200 forward passes
effectively over it basically we take
the image and we convert it into a spike
Train That's 200 time steps long and
feed it through a model um in addition
to this um because in our brain we don't
have really the concept of mini batching
you don't perceive 18 Different World
Views at a time um and then update off
of them uh or you know 8,000 or 500 or
however many big batch sizes have gotten
to these days uh we do everything in a
continuous online updating um and so
because of that we can only look at one
image at a time so if we're doing
roughly 200 forward passes per image one
image at a time this can get really
really really slow um and up to eight
hours for us to do an epac over mnist um
and so when we looked at some of the
other existing libraries out there like
Brian into bindet snn torch and whatnot
they all worked and they all have their
strengths uh to be able to implement
these systems but some of them very much
operate uh like black
boxes with the idea that you can modify
parameters on the outside um but then
you're entrusting that your various
existing Library uh is doing everything
you expect it to mathematically inside
um and what this also does is this makes
it hard sometimes to actually either dig
in and see what those Dynamics
specifically are or even just want to
modify some of those Dynamics and so
what we wanted to focus on was building
something that was incredibly modular uh
but still fast right so you can usually
you have this trade-off between you can
have a system that's incredibly fast but
incredibly Limited in what you can do
with it or you can have a system that is
incredibly modular and can do a bunch of
things but GS to tr off speed and so we
were kind of aiming for the middle of
that with error more to while trying to
expand it to make sure we didn't
sacrific too much speed to be able to do
all of the modular stuff that we wanted
to be able to do um and so with that we
have some highlights of NGC learn here
so first off this is an open source
project it's available on pip it's
available on GitHub uh we are an active
development base which means that if you
write us messages on like if you put
errors or mess notifications it GitHub
we'll see them if you email us we will
see them we will respond to them we can
work with you on them um it is uh so NGC
learn specifically uh is built using Jax
uh which is basically built on the
underlying Library called The
Accelerated linear algebra library or
xlaa which is a bunch of C of cpython
bindings uh wrapped around um basically
C functions for doing linear algebra and
what that allows and so those are really
fast because we get to use c um and then
on so Jax is built on one step on top of
that which basically creates a bunch of
numpy bindings for said cpython
functions um and so JX has this really
really uh cool and uh component to it uh
called Justin Time compilation and what
this allows you to do is you can put a
pure method uh into Jax's J in time
compilation and it will give you a pure
method out but when you run that method
it runs entirely in C it does not
actually do anything in Python and so
the advantage of that is if we can take
our giant models State transition
functions and make them be pure
functions where you give it an initial
State and it gives back to you the final
State we can pass that into Jax's J in
time compilation and basically take the
entire model and its entire State
transformation and we can do it really
efficiently in C um and actually as a
matter of fact we can take that and we
can do state transitions uh hundreds of
times before we ever return to Python
and so this is kind of how we get that
speed up and in our testing that same
model that took eight hours to do an
Epoch over mnist uh we got down to
roughly 15 minutes uh 12 to 15 running
on the same Hardware um for to do an
Epoch over mnist which is you know 40
time speed up there uh there have been
other examples that we've had that have
gotten up to a 50 time speed up uh this
is not me promising that you will
achieve a 40 or 50 times speed up in
your work this is just me saying that
like sometimes you don't realize how
fast it can be running um we also wrote
this so that way if you want to be
writing your own new components because
we all know that you know P models are
great we can work with those those are
great but the fun part about science is
actually getting to build new things and
try out new ideas and new modules so we
made it really easy to write new stuff
uh write new components write new basic
like write new learning rules write new
you know neurons all of the stuff is
really easy to write and they wire
directly into the compilers without any
problems um and then the one of the
other things too that we have is that it
interfaces with uh Intel's Lui 2's uh
simulator uh now the Lui 2 is a
neuromorphic chip
uh developed by Intel for doing
neuromorphic Computing uh this is
basically taking spiking neural networks
and putting them at purely a hardware
level um which is where all of the
Energy Efficiency that you've heard
people talk about with spiking neural
networks comes from uh is the fact that
when you put it onto a neuromorphic chip
it's really efficient um and having
worked with physical Luis and whatnot it
can be somewhat of a struggle uh to
actually get those chips running and get
them working well and so what that kind
of comes down to is when you want and
you actually get access to one of the
physical pieces of Hardware you want to
make sure that your model probably at
least Works in their simulator that they
provide um I will tell you that the
simulator does not one toone match with
reality but that is uh something that
Intel knows and is aware of and I
presume working on um but what we allow
you to do is that we have a we have a
sub project of NGC learn called NGC lava
um and what that gives you is a couple
changed object classes and a couple more
restrictions that you have to follow
while building things um and then after
that you can run NGC models directly in
the Lui 2 simulator um this means that
you can take your model and you can run
it on a GPU you can run it on a CPU and
you can run it on the uh Lui simulator
all without actually having to change
any of your code base you're basically
just like changing a flag somewhere on
where it's running and that's all you
have to do for
that so how do we actually build models
in NGC learn because now that I've
pitched it to you is this great tool
let's see if it holds up with how easy
it is so overall it's a modular system
right so the goal of NGC learn was to be
incredibly plug and play and also it has
to be effectively one giant State
machine so we can see on the right here
we have this context block now for us a
context is generally our model uh but
sometimes you'll have multiple models
that you define or some models that are
defined inside of one giant overarching
context it's just the container that
holds everything now the parts that
we're the most interested in the things
that actually do all of the updates and
hold all of the fun bits of research are
the components um and so components tend
to be consist up of a couple of things
so we have parameters uh and we have
compartments and then there are the
cables that connect them and we'll talk
more in detail about what each one of
those are in a little bit but that so
but the components are the new things
right if you build a new neuron if you
build a new weight Matrix with a new
learning rule or whatever those are what
you're building you're just building
those little tiny parts and because of
the way that they interface with one
another is you don't have to worry about
oh does this have the right number of
outputs to line up with the right number
of inputs and whatnot if you build the
components in such a way that uh you
follow just the standard practice that
we've set out all of the data will flow
from component to component without any
problems so if we want to actually talk
about the components these are the
backbone of what you're doing so on the
so on the left here I have the Leaky
integrate and fire neuron now this is
one of the most common neurons to see
when you're starting out in spiking
neural networks uh it is the idea that
you have uh an internal voltage that
slowly builds up passes over a threshold
and then depolarizes into msah Spike um
and it does that by get taking in
current and you know V equals ir and you
do current times resistance and you get
a voltage and it slowly builds up your
voltage so inside of your LF neuron or
our leaky integrating fire neuron we
have a couple of fixed parameters now
for us fixed parameters are values that
don't change during runtime these are
the static parts of your model but
they're not but they're not fixed across
all of your components and what I mean
by that is that I can have a leaky
Integra and fire neuron like with a
voltage threshold of one and I can have
another leaky Integra and fire on with a
thrt threshold of two um and you can
build both of those it works perfectly
fine but the one and the two can't
change um well it's running uh because
just of the way that it all works out
internally with the compiling but for
instance here we have some fixed
parameters we have neuronal units so
when we talk about having a neuron or a
component that is a neuron it is more in
reality a layer of neurons so for us and
neuronal units is just the number of
leaky integrate and fire neurons that
exist inside this little component or
cluster of neurons uh they all have a
voltage threshold um then we have to M
RM a V reset and a VR test uh these are
just all of the various parameters that
you need to get a leaky integrate by
neuron
running and then below all of these we
have the compartment values now this is
where you actually store the stateful
part of your component this these are
the values that change over time these
are the values that we are transmitting
to from component to component and so
for instance here in our leaky Integra
and fire neuron on the left we can see
that we have current coming in on the
left we have this voltage value that
kind of floats around in the middle
because we're not expecting to put to
have it as an output uh we have our
output Spike which is just whether or
not our voltage did Spike and then we
have time of last Spike uh which is just
well the last time step that it spikes
because there's multiple learning rules
that require that and so what this so
what we can see here is that if you can
kind of think about the various parts of
your model that you like to build the
neurons the weight matrices any other
auxiliary system that you have in your
model if you can kind of fit it to a
component it's incredibly
straightforward to get these to be built
and then once you have them in component
form you can then plug them into any
part of any
model so then uh what we're going to
talk about here is we're going to talk
about cables now cables can be a little
bit confusing at first uh so cables are
what actually connect our components
together so if we look at the top we
have component a and we have component B
and basically what this is is that and
then they're connected with the cable
and so we have our output compartment
which is the brown box that's on the
right side of component a and then we
have our input compartment that's on the
left side of the compartment's box for
component B and then they're connected
with this cable and so the idea is that
data will flow from the output
compartment of component a and get
copied into the input compartment of
component B and so this is basically how
we get data to move from one to the
other without necessarily having it know
where it comes from so this was one of
the main things that we wanted to make
sure you uh was a founding principle of
kind of what we were going for when we
looked at the component and cables is
that uh a component downstreams so case
component B it doesn't necessarily need
to know and it shouldn't know where the
incoming values are coming from so these
cables are all oneway cables you cannot
go backwards up the cable uh basically
the components are just told hey this is
the value that has been transmitted
along this line and thus this is the
value that you have and you don't get to
know where it comes from now what this
does mean though is that sometimes
sometimes what we'll have is inside
we'll have a component that knows that
it's getting values from two places for
instance in the bottom explanation we
have component X and component y each
one of them have an output but we're
trying to put both of their outputs into
the same compartment in component Z now
if we were to do this without the
summation that you can see what would
happen is the value from component X
would come down and it would get put
into the compartment and component Z and
then the output of component y would
come down and it would also give put
into the compartment of component Z
effectively over writing component X and
so but what we do have is we have this
concept of operators which are just
simple uh Transformations that can be
done to the data that are being
transmitted along cables so in this case
summation uh this is you just have two
you just have two pieces of data that
all flow into this little summation
operation that just flows into your
output compartment um it's important to
note that the value like the
Intermediate values inside of things
like summation are never stored anywhere
they are purely just an inline operation
that
happens
yeah so that's all you actually need to
build a model right is you have
components and you wire them together
that pretty much talks about everything
you need to know for the physical parts
of your model and how they talk to one
another but that doesn't get us anywhere
if I just hand VI a model that has a
bunch of wires around it and a bunch of
values in it but I don't tell you how to
actually change any of the values that's
fairly useless um in addition to that
it's not a particularly great you know
just research project we all care about
how do these models adapt over time we
all care about that whole temporal and
evolving nature of everything so with
that in mind we want to talk now about
how do we actually transition a model
and uh what goes into
that so for transitioning a models ACR
so we have state transitions across just
a component so if we just zoom in on
what a component is we have component a
here uh where we have our fixed
parameters across the top here you can
see we have four fixed parameters and
then we have two different state
transitions that we're going to allow we
have the reset
transition and then we have the advanced
transition and so in this example here
we can see that the reset transition
takes two fixed parameters in and sets
values via like the dash lines that we
see sets values into all four
compartments or we have the advanced
transition that takes in again two fixed
parameters but different fixed
parameters than reset and then it also
uses three of of the compartment values
we can see the input compartment value
on the far left and the two floating
compartment values with their solid
lines that go into advance and basically
this is we have written an advance
function so basically this is just we're
doing a state transition called advance
that requires two fixed parameters and
three dynamically changing compartment
values Advance internally does some
transformation of this data and it
outputs two values one of those values
gets looped back into the floating
compartment that we see on the right and
the other one gets sent to the output
compartment that's also on the far right
and that's really all these State
transitions across components are when
we write them internally and we'll look
at some of what this looks like in a
little bit um what we'll notice is that
each one of these uh
transitions is relatively simple right
it's just you just take values in do TR
do something to them and send values out
and that is really again you'll see this
throughout all of NGC learn that is
basically how it all works under the
hood is that we just we take values in
we transform them we send values out and
we don't necessarily need to know where
those values are going or where the
input values came from that we just know
how to move them
around and it's important to note here
again that the parameter parts are fixed
uh it's only the compartment values that
we can change so you couldn't see
Advance draw a dotted Arrow up to one of
the fixed parameters because they are
once again
fixed so now that we know how to do a
transition across one component what if
we wanted to do a transition across two
components and I'm aware that the
parameter little circles are missing
their arrows the images got
significantly too cluttered uh when I
tried to draw those arrows in as the
diagrams get smaller um but what we'll
notice here is that we now can take a
group of components and we can talk
about taking the advance action across a
group of components and so what this
basically does is we will do the Advan
operation or transition on along
component a we will then transmit all of
the data along all of the cables going
between component a and component B the
whatever that outputed value of advanced
state was would get sent into its output
compartment and then sent to component B
and then component B would once again
also do its Advanced transition in which
it would take on all of its values and
compute its own output value and you
could chain these together at infinum
there's no limit to how many of these
you can chain together um I will say
that eventually it's probably you know
might want to look at making your model
a little bit smaller but there's no
actual limit to it uh there's also no
limit to how complex you make these uh
there's nothing that says that you can't
have recurrent Connections in your uh
cables uh there's also nothing that says
that outputs or inputs need to actually
have values you can clamp values to them
um which is basically the process of we
just set the value and then just let it
go but there is one thing to note
especially when talking about recurrent
things and recurrent connections between
neurons and groups of neurons and uh
what that is is that the order of
operations in a state transition is
deterministic and
thus it's also something that each one
only goes once so if you have component
a wire into component B and then
component B wire into component a it
will still only execute a transition
across a and then across B it or across
B and then across a it will never do it
will never actually Loop itself um it
will always do one and then the
other and so now all of this really
really works itself down to compiling so
the compiler of NGC learn um is not
actually found in the main repo of NGC
learn so NGC learn is built on top of
what is known as NGC stimulation library
or NGC Sim lib for short um and that is
where all of the I don't want to say
messy or ugly but that is where all of
this code behind the scenes that are
making everything work exists um and
that is all of that Library can be found
in that little tiny compiling arrow that
we see down
here now what we for the way compiling
works though is we have our state
transition right we have the state
transition that we talked about in the
previous slide and we want to turn it
into a pure operation and what we mean
by that is that it uh the same inputs
will always produce the same outputs and
no value outside of the outputs of the
method are ever
modified and so what how we can do that
is with the way that the transitions all
work is we can just pass in the entire
state of our model and then based on the
transitions inside each component they
know what compartments they have to be
looking at and so they will look at
those compartments and they will then
update and modify the values in the
model and then it'll move from that one
into the next one and from the next one
into the next one and so on and so forth
until it's actually done and so these
are these produce pure methods and if we
think back to what I talked about with
Jacks all along at the beginning uh that
means that we can pass these compiled
methods into Jax's just in time
compilation and so this gives us is this
allows us to basically call Advance or
reset or any transition function that's
defined across all of components at what
like effectively at once uh in one
operation uh here we have it as Advance
the
model and so this is truly where the
speed up of NGC learn comes from um even
if you do not use uh Jax Jax or if you
don't use Jax's just in time compilation
you're debugging um it is still a fairly
large speed up just to go from python
being written like the way it is into
compiling into just running the compiled
operation um so if you really want to
look into and care about how are we
getting the speed that we're getting
look into the compilers um and once
again the compilers are actually located
in NGC learn NGC Sim lib which still can
be found through all of The Knack laabs
GitHub Pages it is also public
so now what does this actually look like
in code uh and so I wanted to take a
brief look um because pretty pictures
are really are you know a tool that
helps us understand the thought process
behind the models and they understand
how the models actually work but
sometimes people will show us really
pretty pictures and then when you go to
actually implement it in code it looks a
whole lot different or things just don't
quite or not quite as pretty of a
picture uh so we do have a short section
here where we're going to talk about all
of the different code that we do
have
so here's an example of a component in
NGC learn uh specifically we are going
to be looking at the DSE synapse now all
a dense synapse is is it is a weight
Matrix uh that has both a resistant
scale value on it so just a constant
multiplication scale factor being
applied to everything um as well as a
bias term that is added to
everything now so here we have some
compartment values on the left so as you
can see uh defining compartments is
incredibly easy so now uh everything
right here where you see self dot is all
inside of the Constructor of our object
um so here we have self. inputs is just
compartment and then some values for us
that's the prev Val so that's whatever
we want that's a it's a matrix of all
zeros of the correct shape and we have
self. outputs which is just again
another compartment defined with post
vals and then we have our weights now
weights are just our weight Matrix uh
which is defined previously in the
function um but it is just again simply
compartment value and what this does a
bunch of stuff under the hood but this
basically actually Associates so when
you build one of these objects when you
build a DSE synapse and and construct it
this will actually build a bunch of
compart this will build three
compartments under the hood and
basically register them inside the D
synapse and Link everything together
correctly so that way we know that they
exist and we can wire into them and it
does a little bit more than just python
knowing that the object has these fields
in it they exist and they have their own
set of properties um and then we have
our fixed parameters which if look look
exactly like just values that exist on a
class right we have self. shape which
and self. our scale which is just a
resistance scaling and I'm sure
everybody here who's worked with python
is very familiar with what that looks
like and so finally we have defining our
state transitions now there's a couple
things to note about this we'll notice
that our state transition definitions
are static methods and what they are
really is they're just method these have
to the pure methods to Define our state
transitions um so here we have advanced
State and we want to still be able to
use our scale inputs weights and
biases inside of advanced State and have
them all correlate to the values that
exist inside of our component but due to
the way that the compiler works is we
still need this to all be a peer method
so how do we combat that well we combine
that by just doing effectively pattern
matching where as long as your names for
the various inputs so r scale inputs
weights biases whatever as long as those
values are found inside of the component
that this transition is acting on uh it
will automatically grab those values out
of those components when it's doing the
transition and so here we can see this
is a pretty straightforward matrix
multiplication with a scaling and a bias
term
uh to compute outputs and we'll notice
that once again outputs is something
that is keyworded on the component and
because when it's done resolving its
transition it needs to know where to put
the output value or in this case outputs
of the state transition like what values
are changed and so it knows how to put
outputs back into self.
outputs and so this is kind of the key
to how all of NGC learns compilation and
just plug-and playay models work with
these State transitions is that you can
Define these methods that can pull in
values from the components that they are
appi being applied to without actually
having to have an instance of the
component itself now there's one other F
uh aspect of these that's not actually
shown in this example and that is
parameters at runtime so for instance
let's just say that we wanted to add the
current time to our output I don't know
why we would want to be doing that but
let's say we wanted to so if inside
Advanced State inside the parameter list
we had another value say time or T and T
doesn't exist on the component that this
transition is being applied to what
we'll see with this then is that late it
will and we'll see this a little bit
later in an example what it will want to
do is it will say hey I can found all of
these values but this specific value T
is not found in this component you need
to give me T for whatever I need to do
for this state transition and so this is
how you can get runtime parameters to be
passed into your state Transitions and
modify them that
way so now that we have a component and
we kind of figured out how to define a
component and I should note that we can
Define as many of these State transition
as we want because they're not bound to
any specific
component we need to do something so how
do we actually Define these components
in a model because generally we want
multiple of them in a model a component
is one piece of a model is not very
useful so in order to do that we use wi
blocks in Python uh for us we call them
contexts uh so we do a with a context
and then we give our context a name in
this case we've named it model and so
what we have here is this is a WID block
and so what it what this does is this is
just saying everywhere every time we
Define a new NGC learn component or
initialize a new NGC learn component
inside of this width block it will
automatically be added to the model so
there's no model. register various built
things no model. components list that
you need to make sure is up to date
nothing like that if we call heavy and
synapse here inside of this WID block
the heav synapse exists on your model
now what this does mean though is that
the names of all of our synapses are
required to be unique uh but I feel like
that shouldn't be super challenging
because in our models just for clarity
and human readability we try not to name
things the same for instance it wouldn't
really make sense if I have three
different parts of my model that I've
named
Z1 so with that we can see that we can
define components like this but what if
we have complex models in which we have
one overarching model with submodels
that run maybe at different times or at
a different frequency and we want to be
able to have those still be a part of
this bigger model the bigger scope of
the model but run on their own well
luckily for you we can do that so
components are sorry contexts are fully
nestable you can Nest them as deep as
you want and when you actually look at
the structure internally you'll notice
that it follows very similar to a file
structure where everything just ends up
with paths based on context
name and so you can Nest these as deep
as you want generally in my own personal
use I've never found really a need to go
more than an extra layer deep but
there's nothing that stops you from
going three four five layers deep um and
so as we can see here though it's
incredibly straightforward to actually
build the model uh this here has built a
model with two heavy and synapses in it
now I'll give you a brief note there's a
bunch of other components that are
defined below this to get the model to
do something um but those all look
pretty much exactly the same as this
just with different objects and
different components being built at
every
line so now we have our components we
have our components defined inside of
our context but they don't do anything
they don't they don't interact with one
another if we think back to the way that
we get components to interact with
another we have to wire them between
each other right we have to get data to
flow from a heavan synapse into an LF
cell we have to get it to flow from an
input placon neuron into a weight Matrix
into an LF cell we have to get all of
this data to flow so we do that with
cables and luckily defining cables is
incredibly straightforward so we have
overridden the leftand bitshift operator
basically uh to say hey
if we're going to read the top here so
unfortunately we end up reading right to
left with this is we're going to take
the ZZ outputs whatever is in the
outputs of z0 and we want to wire it
directly into W1 which is one of our
weight matrices inputs or inp and we
just write that line and that cable has
been connected everything under the hood
is
done and then and I should not I should
mention all of this is still inside the
WID blocks that builds the Contex of our
model anytime we're dealing with
building parts of our model it is all
done inside of the wi
block uh and then on the next line we
can take z1i spikes and we can output we
can send that into W1 I's inputs and
we'll notice that this pattern of just
taking an output and wiring it into an
input um is pretty easy to follow and so
if you build your component with the
inputs that you're expecting and the
outputs You're Expecting and you make it
and you make it really clear to yourself
what you need to do with that when it
comes to wiring up your model it should
be incredibly
straightforward but if we think also
back to the wiring example there was a
point where I put two outputs and wired
them into one input so we can see that
actually happening inside the second
part of this where we connect two
compartments into a single destination
so we can do this with for us the
operation summation and so what this
will do is this will add together any
number of compartments that we put here
so in here we just have it as two but if
we had four compartments that we wanted
to wire into there uh it would be easy
now one of the advantages of doing this
instead of just having two input
compartments inside of z1e is this
allows for a variable number of
connections so if inside of one model
that you define you need Z1 to have
three in
or three values being added together or
inside of a different model that you're
defining you have Z1 needing to have
seven inputs going into it you don't
have to build new components there's no
additional logic that you have to do you
just add them to this list of parameters
that are being passed in and you're done
and another thing to note is that these
parameter chains are entirely nestable
as well so for instance if we wanted to
invert or negate uh for W1 I's output
value so it would effectively be W1 out
minus W1 iie outputs you just put negate
around it and you can just Nest them
down so if you wanted to sum a bunch of
things together and then negate it you
can if you want to negate two of them
and add them it all
works um and I should also again mention
it does not actually store these values
anywhere so they are never actually
inspectable outside of just looking at
the value of the compartment
so compiling so compiling an NGC learn
we didn't want it to be a painful
process we didn't want it to be
something that you had to make sure that
everything was like touched the specific
right way where you're holding it in
with all your fingers and then it
happens to work so for compiling it's
just a list of components and a key so
if we think back to the example at the
beginning where we had Advance State as
the name of the transition method that
we
have that's all we need it's that name
Advanced State and so what this will
I'll do in this line of code here is
we'll do model. compile by key and so
this is on your context model the whole
model uh we give it a bunch of
components W1 W1 IE and so on and so
forth and then we tell it compile Advan
State and so what this will do is it
we'll go through and this just if we
think to the the thing where we like
composition of functions of everything
together it will go
W1 goes through its Advanced State and
then W1 IE goes through its Advanced
State and then W1 eii goes through its
Advanced State and it goes down the list
now obviously if we reverse this whole
list that will change the output it
won't change what it's really doing but
the order that the advances happen in
does matter and it is dependent on the
order that we find here
and so and the other Advantage is is
that we can compile many of these so in
this case we can see that we go through
all two layers of our model here uh and
all of our neurons in our model
everything that's a z is a
neurons but let's just say we only
wanted to go through the first chunk
right we only wanted to do z0 and then
we just wanted W1 and then we just
wanted like z1e that's all we wanted to
compute well we would have to do is we
would just have to put those three
values in a compile argument and it
would just go we can we can comp we
don't have to compile every component in
our model and what this means is that we
don't actually have to have every
transition defined for every component
for example when we're updating weight
matrices we tend to call it evolving
them right they're changing in time
they're
evolving we don't evolve neurons it's
not something that we do it's not
something that makes even doesn't make
sense in the context of most models so
from that standpoint we would only call
evolve on the
weights or we might only call reset on
the neurons if our weights don't
actually if our weights never have
anything static in them I mean variable
in them there's just like there's a
bunch of different things where we can
pick and choose which components and the
Order of the components that these
operations happen in and so in this
again just to fully explain we do have
two different output values coming out
of this compiled key this model.
compiled by key as well as one hidden
aspect that comes out of this model.
compiled by key so but first the AR the
outputs we have this Advance now Advance
here is the pure function returned by
the compiler uh so this is the function
that takes in the model State and all of
the arguments it's expecting and will
return to you the final model
State advv ARS these are all the
arguments it's expecting so as it goes
through and it compiles down W1 W1 iie
w1i and so on and so forth it's slowly
collecting a list of all of the keyword
arguments that it needs to actually
compute this transition so a W1 requires
T and z0 requires T and DT and Z2 e
requires a j what that means is that it
would end up you would have a list that
is we need T DT and J it if if two
things require the same parameter it
does assume that they're the same
parameter oh sorry the same yeah like
the same keyword argument um so if you
have t used across all of your
components you only have to pass in t
once so that's everything that's visibly
returned by this function in addition
what this function also does is we can
now call model. Advance State whatever
this compile key here or an optional
name flag that's not currently being
used we can take that advaned state and
we can do model. Advan State and it's
the same as calling model.
advance and this just has its benefits
so you don't have to necessarily keep
track of the actual advanc function if
you have a bunch of them you can just
name
them so that's everything on actually
how we get the compilation to run
so what if we want to perform many of
these State transitions in a row and
what I mean by that is if we think about
a spiking neural network we have a
forward pass where we take one look at
an image but also in spiking neural
networks usually we have to do many
forward passes up our image before we
actually can before we say we have an
output and so when we look at that
we're doing like 200 forward passes
before we ever actually care what the
output value is so because of that we
don't want to just do a state transition
from t0 to T1 get T1 plug it back in
over here to get T2 what I want to do is
I want to plug in t0 here and then do T1
T2 until I get to
T200 and so for that we have scanners
now the NGC learn scanner is built on
top of Jax's scan function uh which is
effectively a method of doing a for Loop
uh inside of their compiled uh so inside
of their just in time
operations and the way this works is we
have our
scanner we have an observe function for
us but this is just whatever you want to
name it there's no actual hard fast
rules on what this needs to be called we
have compartment values or the model
State and then we have arcs
and so what the arguments are is these
are the keyword arguments for that
specific Loop in time so t0 so at t0 we
would have ar0 t is equal to zero and DT
is equal to say one at T2 or the second
Loop through so yeah at T1 or the second
Loop through this R zero would be one
and so on and so forth and we Define
that down here in Loop ARs and we'll
talk about that in a moment but then
we'll notice that inside of this we're
doing two actual transitions for every
Loop we go through and we advance all of
our state forward and then we do an
evolve step over our model and this was
done on an stdp or Spike timing
dependent plasticity trained model um
which means that we do an evolve Step at
every single forward pass we do one for
for every forward pass over an image we
do an evolve step over the image and
we'll notice that this gets a
compartment values because this is a
pure function that takes in the
component the the model State and
Returns the new model State evolve is
another compiled method that takes in
the current state and Returns the final
State and then we just return the final
State at the end of that Loop and it
just loops and this will Loop over for
however long you give it Arguments for
so if we give it 20 200 Loops worth of
arguments it will Loop 200
times and this part right here at the
end
is just how you can actually get an
output out so this will return the
compartment value located it Sr the RW
Spike output of z1e at every time step
will be what underscore s is equal to
and finally uh to call it we just call
observe it's whatever the name of this
function is so if you named this Fu it
would just be model. Fu we Ted to use
slightly more of that useful name so
here we have observe and here we have
observe then the loop arguments is a 2d
Matrix where every row is uh for every
row is just the list of arguments that
are found here so this is a 2 by 200
sorry a 200 by two Matrix
basically and that gets us our state
Transitions and so this is how we can
look at a model many many this is how we
can transition over many many many steps
with without ever having to come back to
Python and since this is
so scanners automatically put things
inside of just in time compilation just
for the way that they work internally
for JA but what this means is that we
can go from an incredibly slow forward
Passover one image to a compiled forward
Passover one image to a just in time
compiled pass over just like one pass
over an image to a just in time compiled
200 passes over an image and just do
that in a single function that we have
defined this is where all the speed
comes from
finally uh I just want to mention
monitors uh so what a monitor is is
sometimes we have a desire to actually
look at well the internal state of our
model as it's running and when we're
doing things with just in time
compilation we never get access to those
internal States because they all exist
in C and they never exist in Python and
we can't look at them very easily uh
again due to the way that just in time
compilation works you can't put print
statements in compiled code it does not
work so what this means is that we have
monitors and so the way this monitor
works is it's it's just a component like
any other component in NGC learn
admittedly it does work differently
under the hood but that's fine what we
have is we have a monitor by name and
then we have this default window length
what this is doing is this will keep a
rolling window of the last n values that
you define so in this case 100 so it
will keep the last 100 values of
whatever you uh tell it to now this can
now at some point you might say well why
don't we just make this really long and
do it for every
value well that gets really big really
fast if you're storing floating Point
numbers and you're storing millions of
them you can run out of memory in your
computer um so you do have to be
slightly careful with that but generally
if you just keep the things that you're
looking at to relatively small amounts
you're be fine um and the use case for
this we'll notice too is slightly
different with the way we wire things
into it so we'll notice that there isn't
a compartment value right here this
there's no m. compartment name we just
wire directly into the Monitor and this
is why I saying they work slightly
differently um but as far as the outside
user is concerned you just wire into
them like any other compartment you can
think of it as one giant compartment
that stores
everything so here we take the spike
output of z1e and the spike output of
z1i and we wire them both into the
monitor now somewhere in between this we
have run like the observe function that
has gone through and done a forward
Passover and image now we want to
actually look at the states as we're
running and so what we'll notice here is
in view the contents of it we can just
do m. View and we just give it the
compartment that we want to look at and
this will give us the concatenated
Matrix of all the spikes so if Z p1e has
10 neurons in it it will produce 1
by1
um like sets of neurons well basically
just 10 by comma um spikes either zeros
or ones and so as it goes through the
output of the monitor will be 100 by 10
because that'll be all of the compo all
of the spikes for all 100 time steps and
so that gets us the ability to look at
models as after after they have run but
the internal states of the models as
they're running um I will say there are
a couple future things coming with
monitors about the ability to actually
get them to print out and integrate with
map plot lib and getting it so you don't
even actually ever have to view you can
just make plots of compartments and they
will just plot nicely for you um it is
currently working mostly in our
development
Branch finally how has this been used
right I've been marketing this to you as
like hey this is the thing that we have
made and it's really cool and it's
really fast and it works really well but
let's see it actually work in action so
the paper that started this all was this
paper called neuroc coding Frameworks
for learning generative models by Dr
aoria and kefir and so this was kind of
the founding idea for NGC learn this was
built in the original version of NGC
learn about two years ago um and it
built this incredibly complicated
looking model here uh that has both
excitatory and inhibitory connections as
well as a bunch of lateral connections
every line that we see here is part of
the weight matrices and sometimes
depending on the way that the
connections go it's multiple sets of
weight matrices um this is a model that
you can build in NGC learn and it will
look no more complicated than a bunch of
little brackets telling comp
compartments where to wire
to in addition to that we've reproduced
a deal and Cooks paper um from 2015
called unsupervised learning of Digit
reconstruction using Spike timing
dependent plasticity uh this is another
model that we had this is more of a
historic model that we have built uh
inside mgc learn and gotten up and
running without any problems at
all we have uh one of my papers actually
with my adviser Dr Aria called time
integrated Spike timing dependent
plasticity uh in which we built a
patching model uh that does what it that
basically is this whole structure where
we have a sensory input layer an image
um and it breaks up into a bunch of
different sub components uh subm models
basically that all learn small patches
of our image and then we have one final
part that Aggregates them all together
uh this sort of model is also very easy
to build an NGC learn and doesn't
there's no actual time difference
between running some of these um and so
again this is just something that we can
build and this is all able to be built
with components that already exist in
NGC learn if you wanted to build some of
these models this one the tddp synapse
isn't quite in there yet uh but this
model is fully in there you can build
this with every component that we have
inside of NGC learn um and it doesn't uh
without any without you having to write
anything yourself uh but even if you
wanted to rebuild this whole model
inside NG Seer and writing everything
yourself it still would not be that
challenging um in addition to that we
also have this contrasting signal
dependent plasticity which is a
self-supervised learning and Spike
neural circuits Again by my adviser uh
Dr Aria and this is again another model
that like this whole thing gets expanded
to this which does this and this model
is actually inside NGC learn as well all
of the components that are needed for it
are inside NGC learn and you can build
it and you can look at it and it's all
linked to in his paper and what that
kind of wraps me up to here is the NGC
learn Museum or just NGC Museum um and
so NGC museum is a public repository for
NGC learn that houses the biomic the
brain Inspire Computing and the
computational Neuroscience models
basically everything that we've built uh
for all of our models can be found here
um it makes a very convenient place for
if you have code that you want to
publish somewhere um you can publish it
here as just a hey here's your paper you
can it's all it is organized and it's
working on being more organized um into
uh different groupings of stuff there's
an whole exhibitor section for it so if
you have multiple pieces of work that
are all done using NGC learn you can you
you'll have your own you'll have your
ability to have your own folder that you
can all that you can organize however
you want that will have all of your
papers that you've built together uh
which would mean that if somebody is
looking for similar papers that you have
done they can come here and they can see
ah here is a spike timing dependent
plasticity paper that you've done and
here's four other Spike timing dependent
plasticity papers that you have also
worked on as well as here's just other
Spike timing dependent plasticity works
by other authors uh that would you know
allow you to cross reference things and
just have uh a good uh Community built
platform for uh models because as I'm
sure we're all aware it's really
frustrating when you read a paper it has
a really interesting method you go look
to reproduce it yourself and the code is
not available or it's in a git repo
that's been deleted um I think we've all
been there and so from that standpoint
we're our goal is to make it so that
that doesn't happen again and that
everything built with NGC learn can be
found all in one place so we can all see
how much it can
do uh and finally some upcoming features
uh reinforcement learning uh so once
again this is actually uh currently in
our development Branch uh so we have
grid-based environments uh technically
you don't need to make them grid based
it's just the easiest one to visualize
uh so it's using components so with the
way that components work uh if you can
basically chunk your environment into
its own individually Run State machine
um you can display it and run it in NGC
learn uh currently we have rat water
maze rat te maze another model that I'm
currently using for paper that's not
publish yet uh that are all navigation
based tasks that have to perceive the
world around them and uh get updates I
will say right now it is only limited to
2D uh you would not stop you from using
it in 3D you just might have to see how
to visualize it differently um and since
it is built up out of components it is
fully compilable uh and what that means
is that we can compile the rat T maze
into a c function and integrate it
directly with the compiled version of
our um agent meaning that at the end of
the day you can do your entire training
over your RL environment in in C never
having to touch ithon uh and I will say
egocentric and World Views are both
available so obviously these are
rendering the world viiew and then the
little highlighted section is your
egocentric view both of them are very
easily
attainable um yeah and so with that uh
there's some links to all everything and
if anybody has any
questions please don't hesitate to ask
um slightly early on time but that was
kind of the
goal thank you William okay just while
I'm getting back into the game here
maybe just share a little bit of your
journey to working on this like where
are you at in grad school how how did
you come on it yeah so I am a fourth
year graduate student working under Dr
Alexander Ria at the Rochester Institute
of Technology um here in New York and so
this kind of all started so my journey
on spiking nlet started about two and a
half years ago or so and very rapidly I
found just like the speed problem to be
incredibly annoying on like how do I
actually get this to run in a way that's
efficient um and as I started moving to
bigger and bigger models specifically RL
and some other models uh it started
getting really really slow and so around
that time so around like two years ago
or three years ago or so uh Dr abbia had
started uh working on the first
iteration of NGC learn which is what his
original
paper this one was written using um and
then I got a hold of it and it it works
it works beautifully um but there since
that Papo came out there were some
pretty large advancements in the just
computational things Jax had really
taken off a little bit since that had
come out um it was all originally built
in
tensorflow uh which works but it really
felt like we were hammering a square peg
through a circular Hole uh to get it to
do what we wanted and so starting about
a year and a half ago now uh we kind of
set out to make NGC learn what it is
today and then probably eight months ago
it really kind of took off on where it
is with its compiling and the speed and
we've been using it and developing it
ever
since cool epic okay I'll start asking
some questions from the live chat and if
anybody wants to add more questions they
can go for it
okay okay I'm going to read a possibly
unrelated comment but if you have a
thought otherwise it's not necessarily A
a direct question okay Scott wrote
lawyers say that contracts are a meeting
of the minds singers and choruses
experience aesthetic amplification of
group identity here the meeting the
meeting of voices in storytelling equals
a smart mirror for group
identity that's
that's
okay it's interesting I do I do kind of
uh thinking about it is like just my
initial gut reaction to that is that uh
I think especially when we're doing
science sometimes we can get a little
bit too bogged down in being scientists
and not enough time in being like freeth
thinking and actually just coming up
with like new ideas right we get too
ingrained in like ruts of how things
have been done in the past and so I
think I think that's something that we
all do need to work towards more it's
just being a little bit more embracing
of just new ideas that might not
work awesome okay first question mobina
wrote does it only work with discreet
value
spiking no so I'm going to flip through
a couple of slides here so when you go
to these wires here there's nothing that
says that the wires actually move
discrete values but the advantage that
we run into is that the fact that they
can move discrete values so when we look
at here so the weight outputs so like w
like the weight weight outputs are
actual Matrix multiplications of weight
outputs we can see that here this is
this is not a discret value but for us
when we're dealing with spiking networks
the input
coming so the short answer to the
question is no it works fine with
floating Point values as well um it just
also works with discreet values which
many other systems do
not
okay to give you a breather I'm going to
read an interesting quote that your last
comment reminded me of it's from okay
Henry David throw in Walden he wrote I
had not lived there a week before my
feet wore a path from my door to the pwn
side and though it is 5 or six years
since I Trot it it is still quite
distinct it is true I fear that others
may have fallen into it and so helped to
keep it open the surface of the Earth is
soft and impressible by the feet of men
and so with the paths which the Mind
travels how Warn and Dusty then must be
the highways of the world how deep the
ruts of tradition and
Conformity it's a good quote it's a good
quote I've seen his cabin I've been to
I've been to that Lake cool like I had a
sense that you would yeah yeah it's a
it's a really cool place okay reading
down viit your colleague and previous
presenter wrote two questions so first
question I saw that Jax also has a
method. lower to lower the pure function
down to machine code but not compiling
do you see any fruitful exploitation of
this function in the context of NGC
simulation
Library um
possibly so that could get us definitely
some of the beneficial parts so right
now when you compile a function and then
it throws an error debugging that error
is a nightmare uh because it's all
compiled under the hood I would have to
look more into it but if we can just get
to machine code that would be really
cool uh like if it didn't end
up like if it ended up skipping over
like it's going into C but I'm not sure
if it does um on top of that something
else that would be kind of interesting
is and I've actually spoken to my father
who also does computer programming about
this is if we can get it all written
into C or machine code theoretically you
should be able to pre-compile this which
means that you could get your entire
model and all of the state
transitions as a program basically that
sits on your computer without actually
ever having to touch python which I also
think would be a really cool place to NV
direction to go yeah I think I think the
presentation and the package
architecture
reflects it like many octaves of
computer science you're really getting
down into the compilation details but
understanding those is critical because
the point you mentioned sort of by The
Bu that there's the possibility with
only some constraints to run a model on
CPU GPU and
neuromorphic that that that's an
incredible cross
um deployment of of potentially
identical models so you could have
certain models deployed across Hardware
to better understand the hardware forget
the model or of course for sure inside
yeah inside of sim so inside of the
tutorial section of like the
documentation for NGC learn there's a
part with NGC lava and it actually will
walk you through how to run it run the
same model both on the the low he
simulator and your computer like in the
same time um and you can look and it
will get the same output like it's got
some Randomness to it so like your
filter might be in a different spot but
it will produce the same
model yeah I mean what is it even like
to or how is it similar and
different to be programming on a
neuromorphic
simulator so the simulator is relatively
straightforward actually going on to the
physical Lei itself and this is why we
have to stress Sim everywhere is a
challenge so first off Intel's neurocore
which is like their proprietary code for
running on their Lei chips uh while it's
proprietary code which means that I
don't have easy access to it um like I
have a couple working groups that I can
have access to it through but it's not
something that I can just put on my own
machine and test um in addition to that
I micro code is needed which is the
basically what is usually used to like
Pat CPUs and gpus and whatnot but the
micro code it's the level between like
machine code and it looks somewhat like
assembly um you need to write a lot of
your models in that which gets
complicated so until we get a good
translation layer between Python and
either C and then C to that layer or
between just python to that layer uh the
physically putting it on the
hardware still is a
hurdle yeah again super interesting how
this is really spanning the gamut with
different layers of computer science and
and bringing in sure all these
unconventional um compute okay another
question from vit have you also
considered automatic operator such as
when we add two compartments A and B
together instead of summation of a comma
B it is a plus b and the library would
wire them to the summation operation
yes uh so yeah we definitely have
considered that uh you run
into so it works so so the long story
short is like that can work the problem
that you can run into is it can become a
little bit
syntactically uh weird to look at when
you have compartment plus compartment
meaning one thing and compartment. Value
Plus compartment. value being another
thing like basically the problem is that
if we start overloading those operators
it's you now have to be careful like
right now if you try and add two
compartments together uh and you forget
to do like compartment. value um it'll
just error because compartments don't
have an addition with one another but if
we produce an addition with one another
um it starts to make it's you have a lot
more silent errors though until we find
a good way to overcome that problem it's
currently on
pause but this brings in a lot of
interesting category Theory type
questions about concatenating nested
systems and putting them in parallel in
series and what are these operators what
does it really mean when just to have a
certain symbol and then what do you
really want to do what are the
operations supposed to do and that's
kind of been why like we overrode the
shifting Operator just because I wanted
something there that was not just like
do connect um but beyond that it's I've
been a little bit hesitant to override
them okay I'll read uh two comments from
Professor orobia okay first first just
my lab so far yeah but first first uh a
historical not I guess the nod from will
to the old many years ago NGC learn was
nice wink the original NGC learn was
written in tensorflow and started by
offering generic customizable support
for predictive coding first note and
then second note um I posted a link to
where we've curated uh many
implementations of active inference and
Alex we would love to have Community
contributions translating these active
inference models to NGC learn we would
love to feature and maintain these in
the NGC Museum I mean that was an
incredible insight s to have a
package Centric
repository yeah yeah the the whole goal
of this so all four of these models that
are shown here are all in the museum
already or on their way to being in the
museum and yeah the goal is just so that
way like if you guys have this
repository if here's all the papers well
what's better than here's all the papers
then here's all the papers and the code
to reproduce them all in one place
yeah um okay you you you mentioned a few
pieces of this but uh mobina wrote what
improvements are currently being
explored to enhance NGC
learning yeah so uh again one of the
main ones is just getting reinforcement
learning up there and available for
people to use easily um in addition to
that there's an overhaul of our visualiz
a tool tools that I've want to have so
we already support um things like the
raster plots uh all of like for like
plotting Spike patterns uh we support
obviously Matt plot lib does all of its
stuff and since OB all of our NC learn
stuff is built inside of numpy it all
plugs and plays into that really easily
um but we do have um a couple other just
additions to all of this that we're
trying to get up and running basically
there's an overhaul to the visualization
Library
um in addition to that I'm sure there's
other projects that I've been thinking
about but I don't have my I don't have
my notebook with my list of plans in
front of me but those two are probably
the first two on my list is the
reinforcement learning and then
visualizations cool and this is a
question and the help section and the
library built help section yes the lobby
of the museum um yeah and then the art
outside um here's a question that we've
discussed with each of the previous
package developers today uh active inf.
JL and and the RX and fur like what was
the most challenging part of developing
this
out
um definitely the
compiler and more and it's not the funny
thing is it's not the compiler
specifically that was the most
challenging part of developing this out
it was how did I want the user to
actually interface with it because one
of the most complicated things and I can
go back
to here right was getting this to all
work in a way that didn't feel
clunky so and it still isn't perfect
it's just the best I've we've figured
out so far but the the way to define
your compartment in your fixed
parameters and then write transition
functions that can pull them into into
into itself and do the operation getting
that workflow down in a way that made it
so that way if you want to build a new
component it doesn't take very long was
a challenge um that was probably the
most challenging part
um the next one's definitely just
actually getting the simulator to plug
andplay everything together um I could
give another like 3our talk on how the
simulator like the NGC simli actually
works under the hood um because
it's it does a lot of metaprogramming
and pattern matching and function
generation like your actual compiled
method that you're running is like four
step three steps of of like dynamically
created functions deep basically and so
getting that to all work without bugs
was hard um and it's been doing pretty
well uh it's all we've only had two very
very minor bugs in the past like five
months so I'll call that a success in
anology we love minor
bugs oh yeah of course um okay I'll read
another question roric wrote is there an
active outreach program to the museum as
such treasure ought not to be buried
so we're not actively going out and
trying to seek things but it is open
source and anybody can make poll
requests into it um so and we are and
whatever we for like our lab or like for
our own personal research reproduce a
model um for either a baseline or just
as like as we're learning something new
that also ends up in there but um I
think as the going out to people
specifically and being like Hey we're
going to it's a lot of it is as we're
we're trying to get the people that use
our tool to just when they've published
the
paper there that's a very humble answer
also you're doing the active part now so
that can't
be okay I'm going to read another this
is not a question from Scott but just if
you have any thoughts okay he just wrote
things get interesting as our new
computational and information processing
systems computers internet AI etc etc
etc more Faithfully reflect human
cognition active inference and
biophysical models than are existing
institutions and organizations the
latter are historical artifacts not yet
improved and socialized to new learnings
about physics supported
flows I mean I think I think this is
just a my first thought of that is uh
many yeah many many modern AI systems
and giant structures that are made do
not reflect well on how on like are not
faithful to
biology um and we
definitely have a we should definitely
have a goal on making them more faithful
to biology and uh getting
a basically there's a bunch of things
that like biological models have uh can
achieve for us uh with one of the
biggest ones just being the Energy
Efficiency of neuromorphic computing and
the fact that we have things like chat
GPT and whatnot that have uh you know
use power draws of small cities to train
uh kind of goes against all of that and
so I do think that like this is
definitely a way of the future I don't
think it will ever beat out everything
but I do think it's definitely something
that we do need to continue pursuit
of okay I I have a question what is the
cutive or possible title or topic of
your dissertation overall like is this
one puzzle piece or is this the so so
yeah so I've done my dissertation
proposal I off the top of my head I do
not remember what my proposal name was
um but so I do uh spiking representation
learning uh so I up until now most of my
focus has been specifically on the uh
learning rules in credit assignment
plasticity rules of spiking neet
specifically Spike timing dependent
plasticity uh this is my paper um time
time integrated Spike tying dependent
plasticity um and then uh I wanted to do
all of this with the direct goal of
putting it into reinforcement learning
uh which is why one of the reinforcement
learning parts of NGC learn is on the
way is because I need it for my research
and since other people have also
expressed an interest in it for their
research I'm like let's all put it in
the library together um and and so yeah
so I've got that and then the actual uh
reinforce and then all of this basically
played together to go with the
representation learning of how do humans
actually represent stuff because I'm not
a fan of directly going from like pixels
to thought process I want to go pixels
to representation to thought process and
so that's kind of where I've been at
right now in my career
path cool okay another comment from Alex
you wrote
we should also mention that njc learn is
going to offer support for dynamical
systems and even more detailed support
for differential equations beyond the
basics we have now smiley face yes yes
that is that is the thing too that we
are on on track for we've got um
currently a bunch of different
integration methods that are in there um
but they don't allow they allow for some
complex dynamical systems but not every
complex dynamical system that we want
and so the goal is to be able to put all
of those in there too um pretty much
anything you think of that can be
represented as a state machine is
something that we would love to be able
to support
um machine moving pieces around and so
while it works really well for spiking
neural Nets it works really well for so
many other things that use uh that are
you know a dynamical system something
that changes with time yeah from the
active inference side when I see that
well first the reinforcement learning
and the ability to have the egocentric
and the allocentric I think is very
fascinating and and it makes me wonder
how how do
epistemic
value inferences come into the
picture when we zoom out Beyond utility
or reward maximization and include these
networks with structural fixity or with
with a dynamic structure you're doing
learning that's kind of just an
interesting yeah for sure for sure I
don't I don't have any great Insight on
that right now other than it sounds
really cool and I would love to be there
working on it cool well I I I don't know
if I should say that I do or don't hope
your PhD ends before
then do you have any uh I hope to get oh
work on
this I'm pretty sure even after my phdns
I'm still going to be working on this so
I it's all good cool do you have any uh
last comments or thoughts to
add uh not really just that if you are
ever trying to set up NGC learn and it's
you've you're struggling with anything
don't do not hesitate to reach out um to
either uh myself or my adviser Dr Oria
both of us are the on the main Dev team
of NGC learn and we would be more than
happy to help okay I'll just read a
closing comment from Dr Robia we really
hope the active inference community and
audience considers Community
contributions to NGC learn especially if
they want to go beyond using backprop
slst standard deeplearning also consider
using it in the classroom to teach
computational
Neuroscience cool all right excellent
thank you William farewell